1. If a model performs well on the training data but generalizes poorly according to the cross-validation metrics, then your model is overfitting. If it performs poorly on both, then it is underfitting. This is one way to tell when a model is too simple or too complex.
2. If your model is underfitting the training data, adding more training examples will not help. You need to use a more complex model or come up with better features.
3. These learning curves are typical of an underfitting model. Both curves have reached a plateau; they are close and fairly high.
4. One way to improve an overfitting model is to feed it more training data until the validation error reaches the training error.